<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ASCII'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="internet">
	<title>Connecting to the Internet</title>
	<para>
		The Internet is an awesome place. A massive virtual world full of information and entertainment awaits you, may still have just one question. How do I connect to the internet? The Xubuntu Operating System on your Freekbox is fully capable of browsing the web and downloading all those cat photos, and sometimes all that is required is to plug in a single cable.
	</para>
	
	<section id="internet.connect">
		<title>Ways to Connect to the Internet</title>
		<para>
			There are 4 ways to connect your Freekbox to the Internet: Dialup, Ethernet, Wifi, and Wimax.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Dialup</title>
			<para>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Dialup</emphasis> is a very old, near obsolete technology for transmitting internet over your phone line. Computers and hardware capable of interpreting this signal are becoming few and far between, even at Free Geek. For long term stability and security we must advise that you research other internet service providers before considering dialup for your internet needs.
				</para>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Ethernet</title>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="bold">Ethernet</emphasis> connections are the fastest, most stable, and most secure connections you will find anywhere. They are instant to set up and can deliver blazing fast speed that no other networking interface can come close to. So what is the catch? Well, you have to plug in a wire. Once your modem or router is set up, connect your computer to it with an ethernet cable and you should be watching Youtube in seconds.
			</para>
			
			<emphasis>What if Google did not pop up?</emphasis>
			<para>
				It is always a good idea to make sure that everything is plugged in to the right ports. Also, never underestimate the power of a reboot. Unplug both your modem and your router (if you have one), wait 10 seconds, and plug them back in. If that still does not work it might be a good idea to <link linkend="contact">contact Tech Support</link>.
			</para>
			
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Wireless Connections</title>
		<para>
			Many people chose to install a wireless router with their broadband connection, in addition wireless connections can be found in places like the library or in coffee shops. In many cases you will need a passphrase or password in order to gain access to a wireless network. You should note it can be hard to access a consistent, strong wireless connection using free or public connections.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Wireless Adapters</title>
			<para>
				Most people use wireless broadband by paying for the broadband connection and then purchasing hardware to transmit their Internet connection wirelessly. The transmitter is a wireless router. The receiver is a wireless adapter or wireless card (most laptops have this adapter built in already).
			</para>
			<para>
				What the wireless adapter on your computer looks like depends on whether you've got a desktop computer or a laptop computer. A desktop will usually allow a card that is installed internally (a PCI wireless adapter). If you bought a wireless card from Free Geek's Thrift Store and you have a Free Geek computer, our Tech Support department will be happy to install it for free.
			</para>
			<para>
				A laptop uses either an internal card or one that plugs into a port on the side of the laptop. Alternatively, both laptops and desktops can use wireless adapters that plug into a USB port. These are handy because they're easy to use on more than one computer, but can be harder to get working and may not work as well.
			</para>
			
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
